yeah so maybe
you could say something about
[Music] parallels the similarities between
parallels the similarities between
subtly service structure this up to town
and John
I mean the most obvious thing is to as
we
repeated countless long time in inna
talks is the mindfulness that's that's
basically tamales
so whether you're mindful to decide the
talents mindful of the body you can't
stand that mindfulness then only to
practice of the John and she starts as
Buddha said he to start discerning the
factors of the John what everything
necessary for the John
there's also a principle it's the same
principle so that's how I would
initially the go this is what similarly
so parallel it's more like if you have
mindfulness established to the certain
necessary extent yep then if you direct
it in the way of the Buddha described
where the first jhana is that's how you
enter the for John and when we spoke
before you go again
it's a figure of speech you don't really
enter the first jhana as such it's not
like waiting for you and then you do
something and then you enter it it's
more like you dissolve yourself into
dijanna is a stay to jump ship
John is a state of being
yeah state of being that's above the
state of central being that's what he
said he dwells he lives in Jannah having
developed it before head and mouth
existence it's a mode of existence so
like imagine your day-to-day life now
you are and there is a certain level of
business you have to speak to the things
well the isness of a mindful is not in
Jannah might not develop true wisdom is
isness of sensual domain so although you
might be practicing restraint in regard
to sensuality you are still within
sensual domain which means you're still
within the domain of your senses and
sense basis so everything that is it's
within within the sensual being so you
need to make the effort to not like oh
I'll replace this existence with
something else but they were kind of
requirement imply that your point of
view remains unchanged so you want to
dissolve the existence of karma bhava
and then what you have in return is
existence it's above sensuality which is
what the first jhana is exactly the hood
of this car he comes in sets of his
mindfulness enters the jhana and then
whether he sits extends his arm goes the
toilet eat lays down he's in that divine
state of their John because it's not
something you entered it absorbed you
and then you kind of come out it really
becomes your mode of being and that's
what it says having abandoned centrality
beforehand having abandoned concerned
doubt restlessness grief in regard to
the world beforehand you start
experiencing pleasure on account of
their abandonment and that's how you
start living in the John
and that's why it is a pleasant abiding
Weiland now literally pleasant living
and even now everything is pleasant and
in another suitor incidentally root of
the tree it was when an order delivered
was encouraged him to practice John and
he said living under the root of the
tree will feeling like Kings pellets if
you develop your jhana so it's off like
that he doesn't know where he is he
knows exactly but everything starts
feeling delightful so to speak because
the mind is completely on silence and
children and that's where the pleasure
originates from freedom then he goes on
and saying so living under the root of a
tree will feel like the Kings fellows
wearing the rough rag temple robes will
feel like silk fermented cow urine and
feces would feel like onion and ghee and
butter because of the jhana
and oh yes they are the rough food he
gets a bit of relief elected to the rice
by the Kings encouraged so it's not it
you like it still the same horrible rice
baiis we still the same rough robes that
he wears yet developed and divine it's
like pure source of joy there you cannot
even faith fellow because you're still
within the central being so once you
withdraw yourself from the central being
whatever wherever you are you're
unburdened you're free that's again many
stories in the sutras where the Buddha
would be on sleeping by the road this
confidence it's not like you unaware
which means what is truly pleasant is
determined whether your mind is gripped
by the sense of being or not yes same
thing but different and that's what
that's enough for our attention but yeah
you can do this further well second
jhana again it's on
but it's same principle same and doing a
same withdrawal of being integrated a
more purified form of being so if you
really want to jhana you need to first
understand when you're kind of being is
no click try to escape from the current
central being to attaining the John
to understanding the extent of central
domain do for yourself from central to
making you experience and joy on a
constant there's freedom
our thinking in terms of
so first John Oh like you might want to
speak up a bit
yeah the Buchanan's you know described
as one sees the body within the body
there's a kind of seeing something
within
a compact an outline they're like a
minute something that limits sure
containers
that's what I was thinking as if that
same structure apply to John that's all
so that it is it is so understanding
thinking and pondering
within the
understanding the thinking and pondering
for example within the center of the
main we get this amount essential domain
we get this amount essential domain
because there is no sensuality without
thinking and pondering but they can be
thinking hungry without sensuality so in
other words even your sensuality is your
thinking and pondering
so understanding thinking and pondering
within thinking of Andre Villas that
doesn't matter even when you engage with
sensuality is to within the container of
your thoughts
that's essentially never leaves your
mind that's where the sets insult is not
in beautiful terms it's within you and
always stays within you but if you start
experiencing the beautiful thing that
all the things within the framework of
the central mind which is nothing other
than your central thoughts so you learn
to discern the thoughts need to be there
in order for them to be central
otherwise so you get to understand in a
kind of sensual force the nature of
thoughts and that's how you overcome the
central thoughts
all in the same sense you get to
understand the nature of the body as a
necessary container for any sense to
engage me either for pleasure or for
pain doesn't matter what you're exposed
to he has to always be within the
container of the body cannot be outside
of it and that's the same she's
discerning the body within the body but
that other one just means be selling the
body in the right order
yes like so carrying a person as he
seeing the body within the body is
basically recognizing
and whatever in whatever way the body is
manifested yeah
within that within bodies over there
they sure know what knowing yeah that so
knowing the nature of the body
knowing the necessary framework having
that peripheral recognition of other
bodies regardless of what of how
currently that God is manifesting it so
you get to see this body within the body
within the nature of the body that kind
of remains always the same unchanging
because it's always seen on that
peripheral level
and that's why like even be willing to
go to encourage is that contemplating
the aggregates it would be again the
same principle the same office it
doesn't matter if far or near if there
is a feeling or method that your
experience whatever far or near big the
small personal impersonal inside out
feeling is there as in the feeling with
whatever cut the particular feeling
there is mine others this one that
whatever never done a feeling is there
and is that this particular feeling is
seen within the feeling being there so
feeling within the field and by seeing
it that way you know is just two points
of view on the same feeling and you kept
the truth
assuming yourself to be somehow in
between these two like an on define
ambiguous Center and that's why you were
automatically regarded yourself as the
owner but if when you look at the
feeling you want to get to see the
feeling if you look at it to say only
get see perception
the scene he could have said in the felt
let it just be the felt as in not just
all just pretend there's no problem with
what spell no she felt within the help
and then you realize that picture does
not require
in a roomful
seeing the body is this necessary
visit particular way mr. Boddy's
manifested all the feeling enduring
in Jonah first Jonah
it's still because it's it's still the
case that everything is contained within
the body is still using the body has got
that body is now specifically more
specifically manifested in the mouth
well more like your relationship with
that body like between your point of
view and the body is as the means of
engagement gets more more more more
specifically around the mouth
why because once you pass the mouth you
back on to the senses
you're back onto the hands growing eyes
still mouth nose is but once you start
seeing the body as a whole as a
necessary contain and you realize it
okay so you are kind of the first point
of taking up your body is your mouth
since the day you came out of the womb
bit imagine so it's not incidental that
all that kind of revolves for baby in
its mouth that's its way of relating
with the world that's how it works and
that always stays that framework stays
when you become another you know you
proliferate in different ways in
different ways of consuming things so to
speak with your eyes with your hands but
still it's all like a representation of
your unless you become out as in your
relationship with your body on a more
general level than the level of the
state in specific senses you go useful
so every sense restraint is absolutely
not optional yeah I keep saying that two
things are well they people can have
jhana yes of course
doesn't matter if you wear robes or if
you wear jeans it doesn't hit damage on
it but what you cannot have is
centrality so ladies will usually are
the ones who don't restrain yourself
from sensuality cuz the lay life is
about sensuality you know so then you
can't have the jhana but that's all
because your layman but because you're
still ugly drops upset your senses
so you need to be withdrawn from the
center and I don't mean for a week you
need to be withdrawn sufficiently enough
it basically your being gets remoulded
your state of being is now different
it's not a state of oh I'm just
temporarily saying no to this Bureau
together Janice no no need to be so
establish there but you're saying no to
census is your normal state of being now
it requires you to make effort to go
back to senses this doesn't require any
more efficacy became your norm that's
when you're ready to crack to the John
that's why we've been his behavior has
been thoroughly developed beforehand
he's abandoned the centrality in the
grave finding articles way before hand
and experienced pleasure on account of
it and then and his mind gets composing
John
and that's what it said in the first
jhana back to what you said how the body
still there yeah it said I mean that
Souter one by one to study put the
magnifier he said he describes the usual factors
he said he describes the usual factors
of the first jhana thinking upon the Sun
and this is the contact was their
perception was there is the intention
attention that was all there so and
that's what today's experience has as
well so the only thing that wasn't there
was sensual being she leans on my
experience gets different like my
experience gets purified but it's still
the same framework of the same
experience and that's exactly how sorry
Buddha would know that there is more of
this development before he gets the
development he wouldn't get the second
jhana and then say oh yes there is more
you say oh is that more oh yeah there is
more then you develop more and confirm
that there is more because you realize
the same framework still carries on also
she's basically without himself how far
I can take and you took it all the way
up to the sensation of deception and
feel
and that's exactly mean so your state of
being now the framework how it stays the
same in the journal mine is the
sensuality and pressure of the census
organs and that's why everything becomes
alive because everything is literally
perfect equanimity Oh
whichever way this goes it's gonna be
pleasurable the time not if I get it but
if I don't
so this implicit risk which is gone the
entire domain of that kind of dependence
and exposure gone entirely gone
and that's what it will describe it yeah
attention is still there contact is
still there perception so their feeling
is to bear and hope mindfulness Toby
and so the he might need to like you
enter first Johnny to like the
transcendental state outside of your
aggregates or something
it's more like a palace yeah
so Bojana in regards to such a putana
and Jonna I always had taken it at like
said D putana
was the grounds for recollection
recollecting oneself and then it's an in
regard to Jonna because there's that
recollected Nisour the body and the mind
there's not that there can be no skiing
scattered amongst views in the guard key
the experience of jhana hmm feelings
because I mean Jonna is connected to
feeling it's in the sense that it's
supposed to be remembered is it not at
the con district before most feelings
Greta the gratification of feelings it
said it's John there are things that are
felt in John mm-hm
yeah you as I said you will feel the
lights on account of any feeling but
it's all my called feelings normal
feeling is hearing something I connect
my normal feeling to the John it's
undoing what normal feeling means for
you that's how you get closer to a
feeling you Janet to the feeling of
renunciation the pleasure of enunciation
as I said see they said oh sorry Python
is the bassist well sorry Brown is the
bassist and stays the basis you'd
already introduced something new then
with inside of the town you feel the
same circuit on it's still the same
principle of the same mindfulness just
instead of being anchored with seeing
body within the body you see spot within
a thought or you see mouth within the
mouth as the point of engagement with
the body and that states the jump but it
still say mindfulness
it's still kind of peripheral awareness
yeah same principle yeah so as you said
before it's not like when people would
think Oh Jana is the meditative
experience and then I have to be careful
because you know I might not be able to
handle the medical experience or I can
get it wrong that's impossible
if you're getting it wrongly that's not
the Jannah you can't get the John then
you can know it and then knowingly you
can obtain it
or rather establish you that will as the
Buddha would say as in it will you can
be draw your mind but keep it withdrawn
from the entire central be and and
that's what John is so you can keep your
mind withdrawn from the central being
but then end up in company having to
talk having to engage with people so you
might not have the factors of the John
and using at the time but the necessary
base in the container withdrawal from
sensuality developed beforehand from
unaccountably to experience pleasure
that's of it and that's what once your
engagement stops the seclusion is
restored the mind dress goes back to
jhana to the being in Johnny the heart
is the Pali word dwelling in journalism
is living in so these days he lived in
John you know he these days he lives in
such-and-such house these days he lives
in jhana
he eats goes to toilet sleeps in Johnny
there is his mode of being you can't get
my mode of being wrong or rather not
getting the jhana rightly you're already
wrong central domain and if any meditation
central domain and if any meditation
with the few on account of central
domain as the replacement of what you
want of your desires or whatever else
this is gonna be another extension of
your centrality extension of craving
that's well there is no sense is what I
described as well like oh I am entering
jhana I am in the Jannah I am leaving John
I am in the Jannah I am leaving John
he's to overcoming their dependence of
aisle in the senses you establish
yourself in the being of John couldn't
John but yes the ban on his eyes he
might not develop the right view in
regard to his eye he got his I am but he
can't you can't have that in the John
it's actually cessation of that you see
I am is defined by the counterpart of
the senses nonsense basis so I am is the
necessary byproduct of sensual being
it's generally defined as the Appa as
the one who is who is opposite of all
these varieties so we're not all sense
and century
once you see Mount the entire domain
there is no there is no other side it's
like a symptom of I am will have to
cease so show you can go back to sense
domain unknowingly that's how like yet
the to Jenner can get the Jana's he live
be drawn from sensuality for a
sufficient sufficient period of time and
then understood that we drove but he
hasn't necessarily understood the nature
of I am the nature of non ownership for
which you do need some more instruction
but put to Jenner who can enter John
literally practically virtually to
probably need maybe one sentence from
the Buddha just point to the right thing
and he would already done all the work
upon doing everything and also
from his mind and that's why how in the
suit that sometimes well but back here
suit that we mentioned literally the
Buddha told him he's seen like they just
be the scene in heard smell taste touch
then he became fully enlightened out of
hand right there and then yeah I think
what why is it so miraculous because he
was living is this Barker setting for
who knows how long I mean that's Lucy
life covers up with barking elite every
few days and he fully developed his mind
on a country to the point that he
genuinely thought his there's nothing
left for him to do he's fully
enlightened and you think he wasn't
completely wrong in a way he a genuinely
done all the work and then the dev out
of compassion because she was so close
already said actually no you're not but
go and visit the blessed one and he'll
he'll tell you and yet he just needed
one line one sentence and he became
fully lighting because everything was
already there let's complete the draw
all understanding on ownership now just
he recognized it because he was there if
he didn't have it there the instruction
would not have made him another do not
have met him you in a soda bun so
instruction makes you discern things he
those things are there which means
that's what the mind development itself
distrain needs to be done beforehand
otherwise is nothing for you to
recognize so he may have discovered the
jhana oh no doubt no doubt he was probably
oh no doubt no doubt he was probably
quite quite disturbed
whereas today seems I mean something I
noticed when I
like yeah you will discover a jhana
Buddhism and but I know else like if you
just look at the wage-earner is cool oh
yeah however many teachers there are
there are different ideas about what
your honor is so like as soon as you
notice that you start to think well they
can't all be right yes that's something
something isn't listed yet it makes me
think about I mean in the Buddhist time
there were other ascetics others I guess
teachers yep what did they all have
different I mean because there was
different definitions of Brahman for an
arahant and the Buddha had there
clarified this is what an hour on yeah
were there different definitions of what
there are different different values
different set of goals but if they were
doing things rightly they would have
been doing it along the framework of
jhanas or those immaterial
establishments of your mind and
something and that's all like the the
buddha's previous teachers was the base
of nothing in space and neither
perception nor perception was the
highest I mean that's that's
structurally if you were to develop the
same principle mindful that is higher
than the channels which you can only
imagine then how much the mind of those
wrong view teachers were developed but
most people today were familiar with to
the cannot what you wouldn't be able to
fathom in other words they're more
developed then even even monks who've
been practicing the Buddhist teaching
there's neither perception of perception
it's quite the development of the mind
it's all a miraculous spontaneous
mystical attainment no biddeford
neither perception of perception the
same one that then he was teaching just
with the right view it's not something
different they were do it and that's why
when he became an outer hand fully
enlightened when he decided that he will
teach who shall I teach first well let
me teach those who have the least amount
of dust in there are
people like to say and think oh he went
to teach these previous teachers out of
gratitude you know they were really
wrong but out of gratitude because they
helped him in his holy search they
haven't helped him he abandoned them
because their views were not sufficient
he found enlightenment himself and again
he cannot not think from that point of
view so okay I have to teach teaching is
a hassle
that's way they want to do it that way
the supreme Brahma had to ask him three
times and when he didn't decide to do it
he was enough who don't feel grateful to
know it was could be the quickest one to
learn and then he remember his previous
teacher his he was teaching basically up
to the base of neither perception of
perception so imagine that somebody can
get you to the point of establishing
that as your mode of being when you are
in seclusion that's that's virtually
just a step shorter than the other so
the Buddha could have probably insane
that with back he probably would have
just told in one sentence and you will
even that she said it's such a loss for
him that he died because if he heard me
speak his mind would have been
completely liberated for good part
Nibbana right away so he was so close to
the goal but then died away without
hearing the goal and now you know he's
probably reborn in heavens and stuff but
the wrong view will eventually set in
through the round of three appearances
and so then okay so who's then the next
one oh well the next one was the one
that was teachings on the lower end an
Indian had to settle for the five
disciples but with the Buddha 56 today
he was the sixth yeah because okay they
were pretty good in their renunciation
strict the minds were quite lofty
already he told him for the night or so
and they got the camera so so jhanas or any
they got the camera so so jhanas or any
of these meditative attainments and
other payments in a sense of I called
them now I'm in there now about them
I've no idea I came to be basically
surmounting what you are that's how you
enter it which is why you enter second
jhana by surmounting the first jhana
which is what you are at a time you
enter third jhana by savant in the
second jhana which is wildly that's what
you want into the second John until you
settle in the first jhana as the Buddha
said because you're trying to surmount
something you're not even familiar with
if you ladie the cow falling between the
two stones when try to step on one and
me there oh I'll step on this one
instead so can we say so can you say
what is it that you would bring your
attention to hmm if you
established in seeing the body then body
and now you wanna answer Gianna mm-hmm
it's the same say so you believing we've
drawn from sensuality we drawn from any
grief and concern regarding the world as
in you've been investing effort to
develop that it's not like you just
decide I will not be concern about the
world anymore you've been investing
effort to surmount that concern to some
out that sensual dependence and to stay
in solitude those are the necessary
conditions and you start finding
pleasure in that you start to furthering
it now if you want to develop jhana well
you can either attend to for example
converging point of your thoughts to
void your body which is with the market
see that's another thing like you
associate like your point of view you
know when you're thinking on something
with your head behind your eyes let's
complete each other's your mind is not
behind you right
it's optic nerves and brain matter I got
yet you kind of assumed you behind yet
cuz you took the body pretty much on the
level of the mouth first unrestrained
people go much longer in terms of how
far they take the body and the tipping
is on that level of their posture but
through their point of view and the
mouth once you start realizing that
mouth hasn't been speaking for a while
the body hasn't been engaging with
sensuality for a while you get to
discern it as a thing being they're left
alone finally left alone you get to see
their this is always a lot even when I
get to interfere with it it's only
because I can I can do so because it's
given to me as this thing that was there
alone and I can pick it up most people
don't have that relationship with their
mouth they marty's their thoughts when
they think they speak am I not thinking
it through my mouth but why did it
involve the perception of your mouth
when you're thinking
so that's what you start attending to
and basically like like you know I'm
doing something that was joined with a
Velcro which is your thoughts and your
mouth thoughts mouth so therefore
another hunt but that gratuitous
connection between the two there was the
basis for your action for your
consumption for your sensuality is gone
so then when you think about the body
through the mouth that has been left
alone not speaking for a while you get
to see the back of your head so to speak
and sitting there part of this lump of
the body you are not somehow in between
that's why that kind of practice would
lead then to those later ones if there
is an opening is a good essay you go
into direction of gliding the moon
flying in the air and the divine air and
so that's what's limitless boundless
because you stop finding yourself with
that which is which is tied to the body
so that's what I mean you can't just
start looking at your mouth or observing
sensations because it's not about
attending to your mouth
it's about discerning the presence of
the non-speaking mouth in regard to
whatever you're attending but that
attention must have been rounded up and
contained by the behavior beautified
beforehand and by the physical seclusion
then you won't be attending anything too
far into the world and then you get to
discern the peripheral of that attention
peripheral of the non-speaking mouth
more specifically and then you get to
stop converging your thoughts on to that
physical level cuz you you might you
might not see a big deal it might not
seem like a big deal to mind it's still
living in the central being but like for
example the the directionality of your
thoughts and your mouth it's completely
gratuitous and that's why you remain
bound to the sense being mean when you
think something it's kind of yeah and
then you say and sort of you it's just
this natural assumption to control the
mouth and flows into it and now it's out
there in the world no mouth was always
physical focus always mental yeah not
they cannot like spill into each other's
domains and one is all the master the other
and one is all the master the other
exactly and then you lose that
non-speaking mouth is a necessary basis
for your speech
they say one is Maalik Maithili other
you see the connection between these to
suit the direction of connection there
is a connection in as much with thinking
and pondering having thought implanted
one breaks into speech here as in on the
level of the mental domain having have
been had thoughts speech appears on the
level of physical domain but you
assuming the directionality means you
connecting to the sense of ownership
automatically even if you don't
necessarily think my mouth is mine
because there is absolutely no direction
between the two they are not in the same
space so the space that's what are some
of the different domains different
spheres as the bull would refer to like
the aggregate if you want if you if you
have developed the conditions for the
Jannah sufficiently because there is
sent to strain withdraw from the world
physical seclusion not speaking not
chatting just appealing to silence within that
just appealing to silence within that
framework it's all about of what do I
attend next is more like or what will
start discerning peripheral in regard to
whatever I'm attending Angeles and that
is my non-speaking mouth while I'm
washing the dishes non-speaking mouth
while I'm sitting quiet don't speak
mouth quality to the window non-speaking
mouth has a whole new layer of like that
recognizing that separation from this
lump of the bodies are all being there
and if I stop assuming your head to be
appointed you as well
non-speaking now as Bobby exactly
non-speaking mouth stands for that with
bodies so instead of bodies my hand or
said nobody's my feet boat is my growing
bodies my belly everything now body is
the non sticky mouthed the entire 2d for
this so non-speaking mouth becomes like
a gateway now yeah like a gateway for
that we choose to be the body or we use
the gate so anything else that you go
back to body has to be within the
container within the doorway of the
non-speaking mouth